<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Charlotte-Ngs</title>
 <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2014-11-17T06:27:06+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Charlotte-Ngs Team</name>
   <email>ngs.charlotte@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Multiple Linear Regression In R</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/11/04/MultipleRegressionInR/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/11/04/MultipleRegressionInR</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is a summary of one chapter of course notes on Computational Statistics taught at ETH Zurich by [@BM2014]. For all those who are interested in a mathematically rigorous presentation of some topics of computational statistics are invited to have a look at the course notes. The link is included in the reference section of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also recommend a completely informal introduction of least squares by Rafael Irizarry. In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3KFwJd5-JD8&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; he shows how to teach least squares to a fifth grader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A First Example Analysis In R&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with a practical example of a multiple linear regression analysis in R. For all those who are interested in a more formal introduction are advice to skip to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our first analysis, we are using the Chatterjee–Price Attitude data-set. This data-set is part of the R-system and is described in the help file available via&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;?attitude
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data objects are survey results of clerical employees of a company. The data-set consists of 30 observations on 7 variables. The data is organsied such that variables are stored in columns and observations are stored in rows.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us assume that we focus on one particular variable, namely in the variable called &lt;code&gt;rating&lt;/code&gt;. We are interested in finding relationships that are found between &lt;code&gt;rating&lt;/code&gt; and any of the other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data inspection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into any model fitting, it is always a good idea to get an overview of the data by a pairs plot. The pairs plot is composed of a matrix of scatter-plots for all combinations of variables in the data-set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;require(stats); require(graphics)
pairs(attitude, main = &amp;quot;attitude data&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2014-11-04-MultipleRegressionInR/figure/unnamed-chunk-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple summary statistics are obtained by &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;summary(attitude)

##      rating       complaints     privileges      learning   
##  Min.   :40.0   Min.   :37.0   Min.   :30.0   Min.   :34.0  
##  1st Qu.:58.8   1st Qu.:58.5   1st Qu.:45.0   1st Qu.:47.0  
##  Median :65.5   Median :65.0   Median :51.5   Median :56.5  
##  Mean   :64.6   Mean   :66.6   Mean   :53.1   Mean   :56.4  
##  3rd Qu.:71.8   3rd Qu.:77.0   3rd Qu.:62.5   3rd Qu.:66.8  
##  Max.   :85.0   Max.   :90.0   Max.   :83.0   Max.   :75.0  
##      raises        critical       advance    
##  Min.   :43.0   Min.   :49.0   Min.   :25.0  
##  1st Qu.:58.2   1st Qu.:69.2   1st Qu.:35.0  
##  Median :63.5   Median :77.5   Median :41.0  
##  Mean   :64.6   Mean   :74.8   Mean   :42.9  
##  3rd Qu.:71.0   3rd Qu.:80.0   3rd Qu.:47.8  
##  Max.   :88.0   Max.   :92.0   Max.   :72.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A first linear model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a first step, we are interested in how the 6 variables complaints, privileges, learning, raises, critical and advance are related to the observed overall rating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;fm1 &amp;lt;- lm(rating ~ ., data = attitude)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call to function &lt;code&gt;lm()&lt;/code&gt; fits the multiple linear regression model using variable &lt;code&gt;rating&lt;/code&gt; as response and all other variables as predictors. Since we are assigning the result to a variable, noting is returned. But the resulting linear model object has a summary method which shows us the most important results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;summary(fm1)

## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = rating ~ ., data = attitude)
## 
## Residuals:
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -10.942  -4.356   0.316   5.543  11.599 
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept)  10.7871    11.5893    0.93   0.3616    
## complaints    0.6132     0.1610    3.81   0.0009 ***
## privileges   -0.0731     0.1357   -0.54   0.5956    
## learning      0.3203     0.1685    1.90   0.0699 .  
## raises        0.0817     0.2215    0.37   0.7155    
## critical      0.0384     0.1470    0.26   0.7963    
## advance      -0.2171     0.1782   -1.22   0.2356    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 7.07 on 23 degrees of freedom
## Multiple R-squared:  0.733,  Adjusted R-squared:  0.663 
## F-statistic: 10.5 on 6 and 23 DF,  p-value: 1.24e-05
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above summary of the linear model object contains the following details: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;empirical quantiles of the residuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;estimates of the linear coefficients of each predictor variable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;standard errors of each estimate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the t-Test statistic for the null-hypotheses of each coefficient being $0$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the corresponding two-sided p-values to the above mentioned null-hypotheses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some abbreviations of the strength of significance of the above mentioned test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Diagnostics plots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides just looking at the numbers given by the modeling output it is always a good idea to also look at some diagnostics plots. The residuals $r&lt;em&gt;i$ corresponding to the difference of the observed values $y&lt;/em&gt;i$ minus the fitted values $\hat{y}_i$ are useful approximations of the unobservable error terms. The plot below shows four diagrams which are helpful in checking the appropriatness of the chosen linear model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;opar &amp;lt;- par(mfrow = c(2,2), oma = c(0, 0, 1.1, 0))
plot(fm1, las = 1, )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2014-11-04-MultipleRegressionInR/figure/unnamed-chunk-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;plot of chunk unnamed-chunk-7&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top left diagram shows a plot of the residuals versus the fitted values. It is also known as the &lt;code&gt;Tukey-Anscombe&lt;/code&gt; plot. Ideally there should be no relationship between the two quantities and the red line should ideally be horizontal. For our example data-set we can see that there is no obvious pattern between residuals and fitted values. The top right diagram is a so-called &lt;code&gt;QQ-plot&lt;/code&gt; which draws empirically observed quantiles of the residuals versus theoretically expected quantiles, assuming a normal distribution for the error term. In an ideal situation these are all on a line with slope $= 1$. The diagrams in the bottom row are the &lt;code&gt;scale-location&lt;/code&gt; plot testing for equal variance of the residuals and the &lt;code&gt;residuals vs leverage&lt;/code&gt; plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A refined model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at the summary result of the first model fit &lt;code&gt;fm1&lt;/code&gt;, we can see that based on the t-Test statistic and its accompanying p-value, the variable &lt;code&gt;complaints&lt;/code&gt; stands out from the other variables. Hence we can refine our model and check a smaller model which uses only &lt;code&gt;complaints&lt;/code&gt; as a predictor for the response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;summary(fm2 &amp;lt;- lm(rating ~ complaints, data = attitude))

## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = rating ~ complaints, data = attitude)
## 
## Residuals:
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -12.880  -5.990   0.178   6.298   9.629 
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept)  14.3763     6.6200    2.17    0.039 *  
## complaints    0.7546     0.0975    7.74    2e-08 ***
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 6.99 on 28 degrees of freedom
## Multiple R-squared:  0.681,  Adjusted R-squared:  0.67 
## F-statistic: 59.9 on 1 and 28 DF,  p-value: 1.99e-08
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A More Formal Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple linear regression is defined by the following quote from @BM2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a single response variable: up to some random errors it is a linear function
of several predictors (or covariables). The linear function involves unknown 
parameters. The goal is to estimate these
parameters, to study their relevance and to estimate the error variance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the above quote means is that for a set of objects or a set of individuals, we have observed or measured some quantities which are termed &lt;code&gt;response variable&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;y-values&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;dependent variable&lt;/code&gt;. As an example in a clinical study, we have measured blood pressure or cholesterol levels for a given set of patients. The response variables can only be observed or measured up to some random and non-systematic errors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the response variable, we have for the same set of objects or individuals, some more characteristics that describe or classify the given objects or individuals. For our patients in the above example that might be height and weight or some diatary quantities. These quantities are termed &lt;code&gt;predictors&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;covariables&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;independent variables&lt;/code&gt; and are assumed to be known exactly without any errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of multiple linear regression is to relate the predictors to a response variable using the mathematical tool of linear functions. In what follows is a more mathematical description of what was described so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbf{y} = {y_i;\ i=1,...,n }$ : vector of $n$ observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbf{x}^{(j)} = {x_{i,j};\ i=1, ..., n}$: vector of $j^{th}$ predictor (covariable) ($j = 1, ..., p$)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbf{x}&lt;em&gt;i = {x&lt;/em&gt;{i,j};\  j = 1, ..., p}$: vector of the $i^{th}$ observation ($i = 1, ..., n$)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbf{\beta} = {\beta_j;\ j = 1, ..., p}$: vector of unknown parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbf{\epsilon} = {\epsilon_i;\ i = 1, ..., n }$: vector of unknown random errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$n$ is the sample size, $p$ is the number of parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Model in vector form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$y&lt;em&gt;i = \mathbf{x}&lt;/em&gt;i^T \mathbf{\beta} + \epsilon_i \text{ with } (i = 1, ..., n)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually it is assumed that $\epsilon&lt;em&gt;1, ..., \epsilon&lt;/em&gt;n$ are idependent and identically distributed (iid) with $\mathbb{E}[\epsilon&lt;em&gt;i] = 0$ and $Var(\epsilon&lt;/em&gt;i) = \sigma^2$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Model in matrix form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\mathbf{y} = \mathbf{X}\mathbf{\beta} + \mathbf{\epsilon}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $\mathbf{X}$ is a matrix with $n$ rows $\mathbf{x}_i^T$ and $p$ columns $\mathbf{x}^{(j)}$. It is assumed that $n&amp;gt;p$ and that matrix $\mathbf{X}$ has full rank $p$, i.e. all $p$ vectors $\mathbf{x}^{(1)}, ..., \mathbf{x}^{(p)}$ are linearly independent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Goals for linear regression analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good fit&lt;/strong&gt;. Fitting a (hyper-) plane over the predictor variables to explain response variables such that errors are &amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good parameter estimates&lt;/strong&gt;. Parameter estimates should allow for a description of the change in the response variables when predictor variables change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good predictions&lt;/strong&gt;. It is useful to be able to predict new responses as a function of predictor variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainties and significance for above three&lt;/strong&gt;. Confidence intervalls and statistical tests are useful tools for this goal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of a good model&lt;/strong&gt;. Model refinement through some iterative process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Parameter Estimation - Least Squares&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the linear model $\mathbf{y} = \mathbf{X}\mathbf{\beta} + \mathbf{\epsilon}$, we are looking for good estimates $\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$  for the unknown parameter vector $\mathbf{\beta}$. One possibility of finding such estimates $\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$ is through the method of &lt;strong&gt;least squares&lt;/strong&gt; which aims at finding  $\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$ such that the errors are as small as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More formally, the least squares estimator is defined as &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\hat{\mathbf{\beta}} = \text{argmin}_{\beta}\lVert\mathbf{y} - \mathbf{X}\mathbf{\beta}\rVert^2$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $\lVert.\rVert$ is defined as the Euclidean norm on the $n$ dimensional space $\mathbf{R}^n$. The $\text{argmin}_\beta$ operator finds that representative of $\beta$ that minimizes the expression $\lVert\mathbf{y} - \mathbf{X}\mathbf{\beta}\rVert^2$. Assuming $\mathbf{X}$ has full column rank $p$, the minimum of the above norm can be computed explicitly. Taking the derivative of the norm with respect to $\mathbf{\beta}$ ($p$ dimensional gradient vector) inserting $\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$ for $\mathbf{\beta}$ and setting the derivative to zero yields &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ (-2)\mathbf{X}^T(\mathbf{y} - \mathbf{X}\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}) = \mathbf{0}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be transformed into the following &lt;strong&gt;normal equation&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\mathbf{X}^T\mathbf{X}\hat{\mathbf{\beta}} = \mathbf{X}^T\mathbf{y}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, the normal equation can explicitly be solved for the unknown $\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$ resulting in &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\hat{\mathbf{\beta}} =  \left(\mathbf{X}^T\mathbf{X}\right)^{-1}\mathbf{X}^T\mathbf{y} \text{ ,}$$ &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this formula is only useful for theoretical purposes. For numerical computations, it is much more stable to use the &lt;strong&gt;QR&lt;/strong&gt; decomposition instead of inverting $\left(\mathbf{X}^T\mathbf{X}\right)$. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the residuals $r&lt;em&gt;i = y&lt;/em&gt;i - \mathbf{x}&lt;em&gt;i^T\hat{\mathbf{\beta}}$ as estimates for the errors $\epsilon&lt;/em&gt;i$ a plausible estimator for $\sigma^2$ is &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\hat{\sigma}^2 = \frac{1}{n-p}\sum&lt;em&gt;{i=1}^n r&lt;/em&gt;i^2$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unusual factor $\frac{1}{n-p}$ leads to $\mathbf{E}\left[\hat{\sigma}^2\right] = \sigma^2$ which means the estimator is unbiased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Update Mac Os X to Yosemite</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/10/27/UpdateYosemite/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/10/27/UpdateYosemite</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those who want to stay on the safe side and hate to work around issues and new features, are best advised to wait with an upgrade to Yosemite. Also for production systems, an upgrade is probably still a bit early. Unlike with the previous upgrade to Mac Os X 10.9, no real performance boost is perceived when upgading to &lt;code&gt;Yosemite&lt;/code&gt;. Although one has to admit that all the points mentioned here against the upgrade are nowhere near the nightmare of an upgrade from Windows 7 to 8. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before one upgrades a whole operating system, a complete backup of user data is an absolute must. Mac Os X has a backup utility called TimeMachine which comes for free with the system. All one has to do is connect an external hard-drive and start a backup using Time Machine by clicking on the following icon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/2014-10-27-UpdateYosemite/TimeMachine.png&quot; alt=&quot;Time Machine&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Download&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I decided to upgrade Mac Os X on my Mac Book to version 10.10 aka &lt;code&gt;Yosemite&lt;/code&gt;. The upgrade process is started from the AppStore. When you open the AppStore there is a big banner with the Yosemite Logo and a small Update button. Whenever you click on that button the download starts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/2014-10-27-UpdateYosemite/AppStoreYosemite.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yosemite Logo&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took more than three hours to download which is most likely caused by my very slow connection to the internet at home. In total, the upgrade to Yosemite is worth 5.16 GB of data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the download was completed the installation of the upgrade can be started from the Download folder. I have not followed the installation closely, but it took quite a long time and several restarts were required. The whole installation did not require any intervention from the user side. In case somebody is interested in more details, one cat press Command-L which is supposed to show more details about the progress of the installation. The timings shown during the installation were not very accurate. For about half an hour the installation screen was showing the message &lt;code&gt;2 minutes left ...&lt;/code&gt;. It seams that the upgrade utility is copying parts of the user data or installed software to a secure place and that can take a lot of time depending on how much data has to be copied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole upgrade process went very smoothly. The default desktop background changed and the dock looks different but appart from that no obvious changes. When maximizing a window using the green dot in the top-left corner, the window is shown in a full-screen mode. This full-screen mode can be terminated by pointing the cursor to the top border of the screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/2014-10-27-UpdateYosemite/RedYellowGreenDots.png&quot; alt=&quot;RedYellowGreenDots&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Path Issue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/208181/why-did-my-tex-related-gui-program-stop-working-in-mac-os-x-yosemite&quot;&gt;post on tex.stackexchange.com&lt;/a&gt;, Adam Maxwell mentioned that GUI programs using TEX tools like &lt;code&gt;pdflatex&lt;/code&gt; stopped working after upgrading to Yosemite. In the background section of the post the author explains that GUI programs do no longer inherit variables from shell init files like .bash_profile, .bashrc or others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For RStudio this meant that when creating a new Sweave document, RStudio would put up the message that it cannot find any TeX installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/2014-10-27-UpdateYosemite/NoTeXInstallationRStudio.png&quot; alt=&quot;No TeX Installation in RStudio&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When trying to compile, the unsurprising error message appears in the Compile PDF console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/2014-10-27-UpdateYosemite/PdflatexErrorMessage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pdflatex Error Message&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fix for RStudio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the post by Adam Maxwell there were posts appearing on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-bloggers.com/r-and-rstudio-incompatibility-with-yosemite-mac-os-x-10-10/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+RBloggers+%28R+bloggers%29&quot;&gt;Rbloggers&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.rstudio.com/hc/en-us/articles/203815576-RStudio-PATH-problems-with-OS-X-Yosemite&quot;&gt;RStudio web-site&lt;/a&gt; announcing that the latest version (Version 0.98.1083) of RStudio would fix the path problem. After installing that latest version, no more messages of missing TeX installations and compiling Sweave documents worked again. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction To Dplyr</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/10/22/IntroductionToDplyr/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/10/22/IntroductionToDplyr</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Before dplyr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The R-package &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; represents an important milestone in the history of R. Before &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; existed, data manipulation was not considered to be a strong point of the R system. I even remember very vaguely that even John Chambers was advocating in one of his talks many years ago, that data preparation is better done by some scripting language, like python or perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is it all about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; can be understood as a language of data manipulation. The language consists only of a small number of verbs each designed to perform a well defined task. Each of the verbs is implemented in an R function. Data manipulation processes can be constructed by chaining together sequences of verbs to a pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting started&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/dplyrIntro&quot;&gt;Introductory slides&lt;/a&gt; show the basic usage of &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; using Andersons Iris data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; package is available through CRAN, hence &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; can be installed via&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introductory vignette to &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; available through&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;r language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;browseVignettes&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;package &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;demonstrates the application of &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; to the New York City airport flights dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction to R</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/10/14/IntroductionToR/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/10/14/IntroductionToR</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When working with big data which is certainly the case in the area of
next generation sequencing (NGS), it is important to have a set of tools 
or a system that supports the user in managing and analysing the available 
data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The R System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In statistical data analysis &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; has become very 
popular. The philosophy of R is similar to the one of Unix of building a system 
using small tools. Hence the base of R is relatively small. But that small base 
can easily be extended by a large number of packages. The Comprehensive R Archive 
Network &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt; is the main repository for packages 
extending the functionality of the R system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working with data from Bio- or Life-Sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioconductor.org&quot;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; 
is a very valuable resource. Bioconductor does not only provide a large set of 
R packages but it does also offer standardized workflows and example datasets. 
In general Bioconductor documentation is provided by vignettes following the 
paradigm of reproducible research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why R&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because first of all R is very fast in prototyping and second R is easy to extend 
either by writing packages in R or by using its interfaces to other languages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirk Edelbuettel explained why to use R in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UZkaZhsOfT4&quot;&gt;Google Tech Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;R Crash Course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning how to use a system like R is associated with a certain learning curve. 
Some people pretend that this curve is especially steep when learning how to use R. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an introduction, I have put together some slides which I would use to introduce 
R to an audience without prior knowledge. In case you are interested you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/RCrashCourse&quot;&gt;read more 
here ...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How To Get Started</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/08/20/how-to-get-started/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/08/20/how-to-get-started</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most Blogs start by a report on how to get started with blogging. This blog should not be any different. Not that it is particularly interesting, but maybe someone else out there has the same difficulties that I had and maybe these lines can help getting over those difficulties a little faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before coming here I started a blog using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; linked to &lt;a href=&quot;http://postach.io&quot;&gt;Postach.io&lt;/a&gt;. This was very convenient, because I use Evernote on a daily basis. When writing a post about programming concepts, I want to follow the paradigm of reproducible research or reproducible programming, i.e., no copy-pasting of code and results. Everything is produced by one single source file. At the time when I got started with my Evernote blog I did not see how to implement the strategy of reproducible programming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the goal for my ideal blogging environment was to write one source file with everything and then have some clever system produce all the output that was desired. I was reading some blog posts about blogging like a hacker &lt;code&gt;reference needed here&lt;/code&gt; and thereby I found using GitHub pages was what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub offers free hosting of custom web-sites through GitHub pages. All one has to do is &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create an account on GitHub and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;within that account create a repository called &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is to be replaced by the actual username you chose for the GitHub account. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After these two steps, your blog web-site is available at &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a blog-aware static site generator which means documents in Markdown format are automatically conterted into static HTML pages. Furthermore, running Jekyll on your local machine gives you the possibility to serve every page locally without having to upload anything. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Poole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole provides an example setup for a Jekyll site. It comes with a set of templates, pages, styles and posts. This is very convenient for any beginner, because all one has to do is clone the sources provided by Poole, change the content to its own site and a new blog-site is ready to be served in only a very short time. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
