<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Charlotte-Ngs</title>
 <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2014-10-16T05:20:44+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Charlotte-Ngs Team</name>
   <email>ngs.charlotte@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction to R</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/10/14/IntroductionToR/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/10/14/IntroductionToR</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When working with big data which is certainly the case in the area of
next generation sequencing (NGS), it is important to have a set of tools 
or a system that supports the user in managing and analysing the available 
data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The R System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In statistical data analysis &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; has become very 
popular. The philosophy of R is similar to the one of Unix of building a system 
using small tools. Hence the base of R is relatively small. But that small base 
can easily be extended by a large number of packages. The Comprehensive R Archive 
Network &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt; is the main repository for packages 
extending the functionality of the R system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working with data from Bio- or Life-Sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioconductor.org&quot;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; 
is a very valuable resource. Bioconductor does not only provide a large set of 
R packages but it does also offer standardized workflows and example datasets. 
In general Bioconductor documentation is provided by vignettes following the 
paradigm of reproducible research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why R&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;R Crash Course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning how to use a system like R is associated with a certain learning curve. 
Some people believe that this learning curve is steep which is completely subjective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an introduction, I have put together some slides which I would use to introduce 
R to an audience without any experience. In case you are interested you can read more 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/RCrashCourse&quot;&gt;here ...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How To Get Started</title>
   <link href="http://charlotte-ngs.github.io//2014/08/20/how-to-get-started/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://charlotte-ngs.github.io/2014/08/20/how-to-get-started</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most Blogs start by a report on how to get started with blogging. This blog should not be any different. Not that it is particularly interesting, but maybe someone else out there has the same difficulties that I had and maybe these lines can help getting over those difficulties a little faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before coming here I started a blog using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; linked to &lt;a href=&quot;http://postach.io&quot;&gt;Postach.io&lt;/a&gt;. This was very convenient, because I use Evernote on a daily basis. When writing a post about programming concepts, I want to follow the paradigm of reproducible research or reproducible programming, i.e., no copy-pasting of code and results. Everything is produced by one single source file. At the time when I got started with my Evernote blog I did not see how to implement the strategy of reproducible programming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the goal for my ideal blogging environment was to write one source file with everything and then have some clever system produce all the output that was desired. I was reading some blog posts about blogging like a hacker &lt;code&gt;reference needed here&lt;/code&gt; and thereby I found using GitHub pages was what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
